我们已经看了如何滥用FILE结构体
so we have seen how file structures can be abused
以获得任意读写利用原语
to gain arbitrary read and write primitives
但还有一些涉及FILE结构体的其他利用方向
but there are some additional exploitation vectors that involve file structures
值得讨论
that are worth discussing
要讨论它们
in order to do so
我们必须提到一个叫做_IO_FILE_plus的东西
we have to mention something called _IO_FILE_plus
_IO_FILE_plus是一个扩展
now _IO_FILE_plus is an extension
对于我们一直说的传统FILE结构体
of the traditional file struct that we've referred to up until this point
_IO_FILE_plus和FILE之间唯一的区别
however the only difference between _IO_FILE_plus and file
是在末尾追加了一个指针
is one additional pointer appended to the end
就是我们在右边看到的
which we see here on the right
这是指向vtable虚函数表的指针
now this is a pointer to a vtable or a virtual function table
虚函数表是一个充满函数指针的表
now a virtual function table is a table that is full of function pointers
它就是内存中一连串的函数指针
so it's just a bunch of function pointers in memory in series
我们通常在c++二进制文件中找到这些函数表
we commonly find these function tables in C++ binaries
因为它们能在运行时，动态解析函数
because they allow for dynamic function resolution at runtime
这是你在高级语言中会遇到的问题
and this is a problem that you have in higher level languages
高级语言中有类和对象
where you have classes and objects with
继承、多继承和多态
inheritance and multiple inheritance and polymorphism
你可以有一些对象
you can have some object
你调用它的函数
where you need to call a method
但它解析出的，实际要调用的函数
but the exact function that it's going to resolve to
可能在编译时不知道
may not be known at compile time
所以我们用虚函数表来解决这个问题
so we use these virtual function tables as a trick to get around that
在FILE结构体的末尾
so at the end of the file structure
我们有一个指向虚函数表的指针，如图所示
we have this pointer to a vtable as shown here
实际被调用的函数
and the exact function that's called
将由在vtable中的偏移量决定
will be determined by the offset from the vtable that specify
我们能在许多io流函数中都看到了这一点
and we see this in a number of the streaming Io functions
例如
for example
在fwrite内能看到汇编指令
inside of fwrite we have the assembly instruction
call r15+0x38
call r15 plus hex 38
在这个例子中，我们没写在幻灯片上的是
in this instance we didn't include it in the slides
R15是虚函数表指针
R15 is the vtable pointer
所以这个用R15偏移0x38字节
so this is taking R15 and offsetting it by hex 38 bytes
最终会调用这个函数
this will ultimately call the function
_IO_new_file_xsputn
我们想一下如何利用这个vtable
let's formulate how we can exploit this vtable planner
如果我们创建自己的vtable呢
well what if we created our own exploit vtable
先不管把它放在哪里
and it doesn't matter where we put this
可以在栈上
this could be on the stack
可以在堆上
this could be on the heap
只要是我们有能力写的地方
this could just be somewhere that we have the ability to write
于是我们创建了我们的用来利用的 vtable
and so we create our exploit vtable
然后在期望的偏移量处
and then at the desired offset
比如，设定我们的目标是fwrite
so like let's say we're targeting fwrite here
在我们的vtable+0x38处
at our exploit vtable plus Hex 38
可以放一个我们想要调用的地址
we could place an address that we want to call
然后我们要做的就是
then all we have to do
覆盖这个vtable指针
is overwrite this vtable pointer
指向我们的vtable
to point to our exploit vtable
然后当我们fwrite的时候
and then when we get to fwrite
它会参考我们的vtable
it would reference our exploit vtable
调用我们指定的地址
and call whatever we decided
我们再想想
well let's also think about
如果我们必须覆盖整个FILE结构体，会发生什么呢
what happens if we have to overwrite this whole file struct
虚表在最后
the vtable is all the way at the end
如果我们要重写它
so if we're going to overwrite it
我们必须修改FILE结构体中的每一个值
we have to clobber every single value that is in the file struct
我们已经看了任意读写的实现流程
now we've seen from the arbitrary read and write
里面很多值
that a lot of these
我们可以设置为null或一些默认值
we can set to null or some default value
这并不会造成什么问题
and it doesn't really cause a problem
但如果我们要覆盖整个FILE结构体
but if we're going to write all the way through the file struct
有一个值可能会有问题
there is one value that can be problematic
这就是锁
and that is the lock
现在我们还没有谈到锁
now we haven't talked about the lock
锁是一个指针
well the lock is a pointer
它用于管理对文件的多线程访问
that is used to manage multithreaded access to a file
请记住，文件实际上是内存中的缓冲区
remember that the file is really a buffer in memory
所以如果有多个线程试图在同一时间点访问这个缓冲区
and so if we have multiple threads trying to access this buffer at the same point in time
很可能会导致进入一些非法状态
it's very likely that will end up in some kind of invalid state
例如，如果我们有多个线程
for instance if we have multiple writers
试图将他们的数据写入缓冲区
trying to write their data into the buffer
最后大家都写不完整
will actually get neither
会得到一个混合在一起的混乱数据
will get some intermingled mix
所以这个锁的值很重要
and so this lock value is important
它是一个指针，指向某处可写内存
it's a pointer to somewhere in writable memory
我们要确保
and we want to make sure
它指向的值是0
that the value that it points to is 0
锁的工作原理是
so the way that a lock works is
得到锁的时候
when the lock is obtained
我们将一个值写入那个内存地址
we write a value into that memory address
然后当我们释放锁的时候
and then when we free the lock
我们减少这个数字
we reduce that number
这就像互斥锁一样
so this works just like a mutex
所以我们希望它在某个可写的地方
and so we want it to be somewhere that is writable
且它的值恰好是0
that also happens to have a value of 0
因为这样我们就可以访问底层文件了
because that will allow us to then access the underlying file
我们不会用这把锁把自己锁在外面
we won't lock ourselves out with the lock
将锁指向无效的内存地址
pointing the lock to an invalid memory address
会导致段错误
will result in a segfault
所以我们必须解决这个问题
so we have to tackle this problem
现在假设我们已经解决了锁的问题
now let's assume that we've dealt with that lock problem
我们在内存中有自己的vtable
we have our own exploit vtable sitting somewhere in memory
我们覆盖了FILE结构体
we've overwritten the file struct
绕过了锁，并覆盖了虚表指针
past the lock and overwritten the vtable pointer
我们让虚表指针指向我们的虚表
we've made the vtable pointer point to our exploit vtable
我们明确地知道我们的目标是fwrite
and we specifically know that we are targeting fwrite
所以我们伪造的vtable的值全是null
so our exploit vtable can be full of nulls
除了0x38偏移处
except for the plus Hex 38 offset
是我们故意放在这里的
where we have strategically placed
win函数的地址
the address of the very well known win function
然后当fwrite被调用
then fwrite is called
fwrite会调用R15+0x38
fwrite calls R15 plus hex 38
我们知道R15现在是我们的vtable
which we know R15 is now our exploit vtable
它加上0x38
and that plus hex 38
指向win函数
points to win
我们获得了执行的控制权吗？
did we gain control of execution
没有
no
现代libc对vtable指针做了一个检查
modern libc performs a validation step on the vtable pointer
以确保
to make sure
vtable指针
that the vtable pointer
指向libc专门为vtable预留的内存区域
points to a region of memory that libc has specifically set aside to contain vtables
所以我们不能让 vtable指针
so we can't make the vtable pointer
指向我们自己伪造的vtable
point to our own vtable that we have constructed
然而，我们仍然可以影响虚表指针
we can however still influence that vtable pointer
这里的新限制是
the new restriction here
虚表指针必须指向虚表区域的某个地方
is that the vtable pointer must point to somewhere in the vtable area
且在指针最初指向的地方，不是只有这一个虚表
and the vtable that it is initially pointing to is not the only vtable in that area
这意味着我们可以修改虚表指针
this means that we can change the vtable pointer
让它指向一个不同的虚表
to point to a different vtable
甚至是一个奇怪的偏移处
or even a strange offset
所以我们多少可以控制要调用的函数
so we have some control and influence over what function will be called
但我们被限制在这个虚表区域内的函数
but we are restricted to mostly functions that are inside this vtable area
这意味着有很多有趣的候选函数
so that means that there are a number of interesting candidates
FILE结构体漏洞利用中，常用的一个是
now one of the ones that is commonly used for file structure exploits
这个IO_wfile_overflow
is to try and call this IO_wfile_overflow
想调用IO_wfile_overflow的原因
and the reason that we want to try and get IO_wfile_overflow called
是因为它调用了do_allocbuf
is because it calls do_allocbuf
do_allocbuf有什么用
okay what's the big deal about do_allocbuf
do_allocbuf
well do_allocbuf
使用了另一个虚表
uses another vtable
它位于FILE结构体的wide_data成员中
that is located in the wide_data member of the file structure
它访问这个虚表时，不需要验证
and it accesses this vtable without that verification step
那么wide_data是什么呢
so what is wide_data
我们一直在提到新的字段
we just keep coming up with new fields here
wide_data是现代FILE结构体中存在的另一个字段
well wide_data is yet another field that exists in modern file structs
它用于处理宽字符流
it was created to handle wide character streams
不光是Unicode
not specifically Unicode
还包括别的多字节的流
but streams that involve characters that are multi byte
wide_data的定义是
now the definition of the wide_data
wide_data实际上是一个结构体
is the wide_data is in fact a struct in and of itself
非常类似于
is very similar to the definition of the file struct
我们在第一节课讨论过的FILE结构体的定义
that we discussed earlier in the first lecture
它包含我们这节课提到的vtable指针
and that includes this vtable pointer that we just introduced in this lecture
我强烈建议大家点击这张幻灯片上的链接
I'd highly encourage you to click the link in this slide
查看wide_data结构体的源码定义
to see the literal definition of the wide_data struct
我们现在有了完成这个攻击所需的所有信息
we now have all of the information necessary to pull off this exploit
首先，我们要设置文件的wide_data
first we're going to set the file's wide_data
指向内存中的某处
to be somewhere in memory
这个wide_data有一个虚函数表
and that wide_data has a vtable
我们将这个vtable指向我们的vtable
we're going to set that vtable to point to our exploit vtable
接下来，我们覆盖FILE结构体的虚函数表
next we'll overwrite the file struct's vtable
这样好让IO_wfile_overflow被调用
such that IO_wfile_overflow will get called
当它被调用时
now when that gets called
do_allocbuf就会被调用
do_allocbuf is called
do_allocbuf将参考FILE的wide_data虚表
do_allocbuf will reference the file wide_data vtable
然后调用写在那里的函数
to then call the function that is written there
而且它调用时不会被检查
and it will do so with no check
这涉及到了很多成员
now there's a lot of moving components here
所以我不会在一节课上做一个完整的利用
so I don't want to do this full exploit here during a lecture
但我至少可以在GDB中看看这个
but I can at least take a look at this in GDB
这样我们就能知道发生了什么
so we can get an idea of what's going on
好的，我们左边的是
all right so what we have here on the left hand side
一个有漏洞的C程序
is a vulnerable C program
这个程序非常慷慨
this program is extremely generous
这里我们有一个win函数
but what we have here is we have a vulnerable win function
main会泄露win的地址
main is going to leak out the address of win
它还会告诉我们libc中puts的地址
it's also going to tell us where puts is inside of libc
然后它将fopen /dev/null
it's then going to call fopen on /dev/null
然后它让我们能写任意值到栈中
next it will allow us to read into the stack whatever we want
栈上有一个巨大的缓冲区
there is a giant buffer sitting on the stack here
它告诉我们这个缓冲区的位置
and it tells us the location of this buffer
然后让我们可以把我们想写的东西写进去
and then allows us to write whatever we want into it
最后程序会提示我们
lastly the program will let us know
我们可以覆盖FILE结构体
that we can overwrite the file struct
然后让我们这样做
and then allows us to do so
然后调用fwrite这个FILE结构体
it then calls fwrite on the file struct
然后调用exit
and then calls exit
因为它调用了exit
now because it calls exit
我们不能用任意写覆盖栈上的返回地址
we can't use an arbitrary write to overwrite the saved rip
如果我们编译这个
and if we compile this
我们将会看到
we'll see
我们开启了完整的RELRO
that we also have full RELRO
所以我们针对GOT做一些花哨的操作
so we can't do anything fancy here with the GOT
我们来看看这个程序正常是如何运行的
so let's look at how this program runs normally on its own
我们开始
we do start
中断在main开头
now break at the beginning of main
我感兴趣的是
what I'm interested in though
没使用利用payload时，fread正常是怎么样的
is what happens at fread just in normal operation without an exploit payload
或者是fwrite
so or fwrite
我们在fwrite处设置一个断点
so let's set a breakpoint at fwrite
然后继续
and continue forward
遇到要输入的地方
anywhere that it's prompting for input
我就敲回车
I'm just going to hit return
现在我们在fwrite中
so now we are here in fwrite
我们看一下它的汇编代码
and if we look at the disassembly of it
我们往下划一点
we scroll down here a little bit
我们应该能看到
we should see
一个调用
a call
我们看到了一个call指令
we do we see a call instruction
实际上这个调用指令
and in fact this call instruction
和之前幻灯片上展示的是一个
is the same instruction that was shown in the slides earlier
在fwrite + 179处
so at fwrite plus 179
我们调用了R15+0x38
we will call whatever is at R15 plus hex 38
所以我们在fwrite+179处设置一个断点
so let's set a breakpoint at fwrite plus 179
现在我们在fwrite + 179
okay we are now at fwrite plus 179
我们来看看R15是什么
and let's take a look at what is R15
R15就是这个地址
so R15 is just kind of this address
这对我们来说没什么意义
this doesn't have a whole lot of meaning to us
但我们在调用栈中看到了
but we do see in the backtrace here
我们把指向FILE结构体的指针，作为fwrite的参数
that we have the pointer to the file struct as an argument to fwrite
我们可以打印这个FILE指针
so we can print this file pointer
注意，GDB识别出这是一个指向FILE结构体的指针
now notice that GDB identifies that this is a pointer to a file struct
这意味着
what this means
我们可以解引用FP
is that we can dereference FP
现在我们看到了结构体的各个字段
and now we see the fields of that struct
有带有0xfbad的flags
we have the flags with 0xfbad
以及我们之前讨论过的其他熟悉的东西
as well as other familiar things that we've talked about earlier
现在我看不到的是vtable指针
now what I don't see here is the vtable entry
因为虚表指针应该在这个的末尾
because the vtable entry should be at the end of this
这是因为GDB将其视为FILE指针
and that's because GDB is treating this as a file pointer
所以我们需要对它进行强制转换
and so we'll need to cast it
转成一个_IO_FILE_plus指针
to be an _IO_FILE_plus pointer
现在我们看到FILE结构体
now we see the file struct that is embedded in the file
以及vtable指针
as well as the vtable entry
那么R15是什么呢
so what was that R15 again
R15是FILE结构体中的虚表指针
R15 is this vtable entry from the file struct
所以这是我们可以控制的
so this is something that we would have control over
GDB中，虚表看起来是什么样的呢
now what does a vtable look like in GDB
可以查看R15指向地址后的20个地址单位
we can examine 20 addresses at R15
我们看看有什么
let's see what's there
现在我们看到
now we see
这是_io_file_jumps虚表
this is the _IO_file_jumps vtable
这些是它里面的所有函数
and these over here are all functions that are in it
现在如果我打印更多的地址
now if I print more addresses
我们立马能看到_IO_file_jumps虚表后
we'll see that immediately after the file jumps vtable
是_IO_str_jumps虚表
is an _IO_str_jumps vtable
我们可以继续输出更多前面，或者后面的地址
and we could continue to dump out more addresses ahead or behind
查看这个区域有什么函数
to see what functions are in this region
这些都是有效的跳转目标
and all of these are valid jump targets
能满足libc对vtable指针的合法性校验
as far as libc's vtable pointer validation is concerned
所以我们可以修改虚表指针
so we could possibly change our vtable pointer
不再指向_io_file_jumps的开头
instead of pointing to this _IO_file_jumps the beginning of that
而是指向这里的任意位置
it could be anywhere in here
控制实际调用的函数
to control what is actually called
我们说过
now we said that
程序的指令
the instruction
会调用R15+0x38处
is the going to call whatever is at R15 plus hex 38
我们看看这里有什么
so let's see what that is
它会调用_IO_new_file_xsputn
well it's going to call _IO_new_file_xsputn
我们应该在这里看到
which we should see right here
之所以会调用这个函数
and the reason that this is the function that's called
是因为它距离虚表开头0x38字节
is because it is hex 38 away from the vtable entry
所以通过移动虚表指针
so by moving the vtable pointer to point somewhere else
不管虚表指针指向哪里
wherever the vtable pointer points
将之加0x38
if we add hex 38 to it
就是将要执行或调用的函数
that is what function will get executed or called
现在我们可以步入这个函数
now we can step inside this function
但这不是很有趣
but this isn't very interesting
这是它在开始应该有的行为
this is how it's supposed to behave kind of out the gate
我们把这个执行完
so let's just finish this out
我们看到它正常退出了
and we see that it exited normally
现在我们要运行我的漏洞利用代码
now we are going to run my exploit code
看看它有什么不同的表现
and see how it behaves differently
这是fwrite的开头
so here we are at the beginning of fwrite
我们可以把断点设在fwrite + 179
and we can probably set that same breakpoint to be at fwrite plus 179
现在我们回到这里
now we're back here
这里有R15
we have R15
我们应该有FILE指针
and we should have our file pointer
你能注意到没有设置flags
now you'll note that I don't have the flags set
这是因为我们在GDB中看到的这个FILE结构体
and that's because this file struct that we're seeing in GDB
是利用脚本注入的FILE结构体
is my exploit file struct
我们还是需要强制转换它，才能看到虚表
but we still need to cast it in order to see that vtable
现在能看到我已经覆盖了虚表
now we see that I've overwritten the vtable entry
这样它就会跳转到这个特定的地址
such that it will jump to this specific address
这是虚表的位置
that's where the vtable is
如果我们看一下
and if we look at
这个地址加上0x38
this address plus HEX 38
我精心设计了这个
I have crafted this such that
当执行此调用指令时
when this call instruction is executed
它将跳转到0x38 + 这个地址
it is going to jump to Hex 38 + this address
这会把我转到IO_wfile_overflow
and that will send me to IO_wfile_overflow
就是我们在幻灯片中提到的
which is what we mentioned in the slides
我们步入它
so let's step into that
现在我在wfile_overflow中
now here I am in wfile overflow
如果继续执行
if we march forward here
我们现在调用wdoallocbuf
we now call wdoallocbuf
这是我们想要的
now this is where we want to be
你会在这里看到
you'll see right here
在解引用RDI+ 0xa0处
at this dereference of RDI+ 0xa0
这是取RDI中的FILE结构体
this is taking the file struct which is what's in RDI
并获取wide_data值
and grabbing the wide_data value
它在FILE结构体内0xa0偏移处
which is 0xa0 into the file struct
它把wide_data指针放入了RAX
so it's putting that wide_data pointer into RAX
实际上是的
actually though yeah
随着我们的前进
and as we move forward
在这里
right here
我们看到RAX，它是我们的wide_data指针
we see RAX which is our wide_data pointer
加上偏移，以获得wide_data结构体的虚表
being offset to get the vtable of the wide_data struct
它被放进RAX
and that is now being moved into RAX right here
如果我们继续执行一个指令
so if we step one more
这是wide_data结构体地址
this right here is my wide_data struct
我们应该能在我的FILE结构体中看到
we should see that
7748，这里
7748 right here in my file struct
我已经构造好了
I have constructed it
这样wide_data指针就是这个值
such that the wide_data pointer is this value
就是我们在RAX看到的
which is what we see right here in RAX
我们再步入这个
so as we step through this
我们现在要解引用或者说
we're now going to be dereferencing or
从wide_data指针取出偏移量，以获取虚表
pulling an offset from the wide_data pointer to get the vtable
现在这个RAX
so now this RAX
是FILE结构体中wide_data的虚表
is my vtable in the wide_data struct that is in the file struct
这里的这个call
and this final call here
会来到wide_data虚表中偏移0x68处
is offsetting the vtable in the wide_data struct in the file struct by 0x68
我们看看我的利用脚本设置了什么
let's see what my exploit has that set to
这会调用win函数
this is going to call the win function
如果我们继续
and if we continue
会报段错误
it segfaults
但你知道段错误前它做了什么
but you know what it did before it segfaulted
它输出了you win
it said you win
所以我们能够
so we were able
利用这些虚函数表
to take advantage of these virtual function tables
去执行任何我们想要执行的
to execute whatever we wanted
我没有在演示中展示利用脚本的代码
now I didn't show the exploit code in the demo
这是有原因的
and there was a good reason for that
这个模块的很大一部分题目
a large part of the challenge of this module
是思考如何满足这些要求
is reasoning about how to meet these requirements
以在限制下完成虚表利用
to pull off a vtable exploit in a restricted environment
以及如何思考结构体
and how do we think about structs
如何考虑指向结构体的指针
or how do we think about a pointer to a struct
以及指针指向结构体，它的成员变量又是指针的情况
or a pointer to a struct that has a member that is a pointer
做这个内存探索
kind of doing this this memory map
建立一个处理它的思考模型
and having a model of working with that
对我来说，GDB是一个了不起的工具
now for me GDB is an amazing tool
可以助我理清处理它的思路
to kind of march my way through this
所以我强烈推荐
and so I'd strongly recommend
如果你已经放弃GDB，请再试一次
that you give gdb another try if you have forsaken the tool
因为我这个例子很慷慨
because my example challenge here was extremely gracious
它给我们泄露了很多信息
it gave us a lot of leaks
它给了我们一整页的内存，能放任何想放的东西
it gave us a whole page of memory for us to place whatever we'd like
不是说我的利用脚本使用了这一整页内存
I'm not saying that my exploit used this whole page of memory
但如果我写入一个完整的虚表
but if I wrote a whole vtable
再来一个虚表
and then another vtable
再接着一个FILE结构体
and then a file struct
还有wide_data结构体
and then a wide_data struct
如果我把这些都写在内存中
and I wrote all of that into memory
我会使用相当大的空间
I'm going to start using quite a bit of space
现在
now
你可以成功实施虚表指针利用
you can still pull off a vtable pointer exploit
或者说利用虚表指针
or exploit the vtable pointer
而不需要占用大量内存
without needing a massive amount of space
方法是利用重叠结构体
and the way that you do that is by overlapping structs
所以这个模块中，不光要求
so not only will this module ask you
理解结构体和里面的偏移量
to reason about structs and the offsets into them
以及一个指针指向一个结构体
and how a pointer to a struct
它的成员也是一个指针
and then an offset to it that is a pointer
以及如何在内存中设置它
and how to kind of set that up in memory
但随着限制越来越严格
but as the restrictions get a little bit tighter here
你将必须使用一块小内存
you'll have to use a small memory region
来表示一个以上的结构体
to represent more than one struct
方法是
and the way that you do that is you recognize
你要认识到，真正有用的值
that the only values that truly matter
对于你的利用脚本来说
as far as the execution path that your exploit is going to take
是实际要访问的值
are the values that are actually accessed
假如在某处有一个结构体
if I say that there is a struct somewhere
但唯一会被访问的是0x20偏移处
but the only value that's accessed is the struct plus hex 20
那么这整个结构体中唯一有价值的值是
then the only value that matters in that entire struct
0x20偏移处的值
is the bytes there that are written at the pointer plus hex 20
所以你可以利用这一点
and so you can use this knowledge
在内存中放置几个结构体
to place several structs in memory
但实际上都在同一个地方
effectively in the same place
因为只要这些结构体中会被访问的值不重叠就行
because the only values of those structs that are being accessed do not overlap
这肯定需要一些实验和对GDB的使用
now this will definitely take a little bit of experimenting and playing around with GDB
才能推出如何实现
to reason about how exactly this works
但当你理解并应用在利用脚本中，它会是很强大的东西
but it's an extremely powerful thing to realize in apply in your exploits
另一个要注意的
on an unrelated note
FILE结构体是链在一起的
file structs are chained
它们实际上在一个链表中
they're actually in a linked list
原因是
and the reason for this
有时缓冲区数据不会被flush掉
is because sometimes the buffers don't get flushed
你可以调用fwrite，但这不能保证
you can call fwrite and that there's no guarantee
当fwrite被调用时，数据会写到文件
that that gets flushed out to a file when fwrite is called
写入的数据在缓冲区中
it could just be sitting in the buffer
那么，如果调用fwrite后exit会怎样
so what happens if you call fwrite and then exit
流函数
well the streaming functions
或者说库的流组件
or the streaming components of the library here
会确保这些数据被写入到文件中
have to make sure that that data does get flushed out to the file
它会遍历这个链表
and so it will go through this linked list
写入到所有对应文件
to flush all of the files and ensure that
并确保写缓冲区代表的写入真的发生
all of the representative region wirtes have in fact occurred
如果你看一下你程序打开文件的FILE链表
and if you explore the chain on a file that's opened  in like your user program
你会发现
you will find
在链表最下面是
down the link list
标准输入，标准输出，标准错误
standard in standard out and standard err
只是一种随机的??
just as a kind of random ??
这个FILE结构体链表
so these chained file structs
的确有利用方法
do have a exploitation use
我们知道每个为了写而打开的文件，都会flush入文件
if we know that every file that's open for writing needs to get flushed
而且flush这个动作
and we know that the act of flushing the file stream
会用到虚函数和虚表
is going to use virtual functions and a vtable
并且存在我们上面讨论的漏洞
and is vulnerable to the type of exploit that we discussed up here
那么我们就可以对多个FILE结构体进行虚表漏洞利用
then we could perform a vtable exploit on multiple file structs
这就不只是调用一个win函数了
such that instead of calling a win function
每个FILE结构体都有一个虚表漏洞
each file struct has a vtable exploit
能当作一个ROPgadget
that runs one ROP gadget
然后你就可以
you can then
把每个关闭前flush的FILE，当作一个gadget
call one gadget for every file that is getting flushed at close
并利用FILE结构体的清理过程，进行ROP
and effectively rop through the cleanup of the file structs
这就是所谓的面向文件流编程
this is known as file stream oriented programming
非常疯狂的东西
very crazy stuff
说到文件结构体
so while on the topic of file structs
和文件流，算是这种利用的厉害之处
and file streams kind of the power of this type of exploit
尤其是针对FILE结构体的虚表指针的改动
particularly messing around with the file struct vtable pointer
不得不提到一篇博客
it's worth mentioning a blog post
它的标题为Angry FSROP
that is entitled Angry FS ROP
这是亚利桑那州立大学seccomp实验室中一名博士生的博客文章
and this is a blog post by one of the ASU seccomp Labs PhD students
Kylebot
你可能在pwn.college的discord频到中看到过他
you may have seen him in the pwn College Discord from time to time
凯尔所做的是
and what Kyle did
他意识到针对虚表指针的限制
is he realized that the limitation on the vtable pointer
其实是一个很大的空间
is a innumerable space
于是他决定用angr枚举它
and so he decided to use angr to enumerate
看看有哪些可执行的
what possible execution states are there
每个虚表指针
for every vtable entry
将虚表指针设置为
for setting the vtable to be
任何能通过libc内存校验的值
anything that it possibly could be within that validated libc memory region
在这个过程中
while doing so
他发现了这里存在的一些新的利用技术
he was able to discover some new exploitation techniques that exist there
我就不剧透这篇博客了
I'm not going to spoil the blog post
如果你有时间
so if you do have the time
我强烈建议你去看看
I'd highly recommend to check it out
因为这就在几个月前发出的
as this was just a few months ago
全新的FILE结构体利用技术
a brand new file struct techniques being published
肯定是很酷的东西
definitely some cool stuff